<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treuue nyeuu tydynges of the wo[n]derfull worckes of the rebaptisers of Mu[n]ster in Westuaell how the cete haethe bene wo[n]ne and in what mannar the kinge is taeken, and all their deades and intencyons haethe taeken an ende [et]c. Iohu[n] of Ley a kinge of nyew Iherusalem and of the hoole vniuerall worlde beynghe in the aege of. xxvi. years. Aetatis 26</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1535</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19230</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 564</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113302</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848538</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848538</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13638</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19230)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13638)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 641:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treuue nyeuu tydynges of the wo[n]derfull worckes of the rebaptisers of Mu[n]ster in Westuaell how the cete haethe bene wo[n]ne and in what mannar the kinge is taeken, and all their deades and intencyons haethe taeken an ende [et]c. Iohu[n] of Ley a kinge of nyew Iherusalem and of the hoole vniuerall worlde beynghe in the aege of. xxvi. years. Aetatis 26</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>M. de Keyser,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Antwerp :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1535?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Woodcut vignette on title page.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Münster --  Church history --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13638:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13638:1"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A treuue nyeuu tydynges of the wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derfull worckes of the Rebaptiſers of Mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſter in Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaell / how the cete haethe bene wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne and in what mannar the kinge is taeken / and all their deades and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tencyons haethe taeken an ende &amp;c:</p>
            <p>¶Iohu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Ley a kinge of nyew Iheruſalem and of the hoole vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall worlde Beynghe in the aege of. xxvi. years.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>Aetatis 26</head>
               <figDesc>portrait of John of Ley, merchant taylor and elected King of Munster, styled New Jerusalem, with hat and crown, chain of office, sceptre and crossed swords</figDesc>
            </figure>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:13638:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>here hath bene hetherto many and manyfolde letters a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d writinges / of the wonderfull deades / and intencyons of the rebaptiſers / of Munſter in weſtuaell haeth bene writ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten of many great aſſautes a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d batailes / the which haeth beene done of boeth partes as well fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> without the cite as fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in. So is now the mooſt ſhorteſte concluded all thinges how it is and haeth bene becauſe not to be greuous vnto the Reader / and in eſpecial how all their deades and intencions after the cite was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken is ended.</p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ow be it that it is well knowen vnto all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and manifeſte that the rebaptiſers of Mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſter in weſtuaell haeth choſen amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge them a kinge whoſe name was Ihon of Ley a teyllou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re &amp;c. the which they haue crowned with a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtly crowne of golde / and ſtreight fourth haue taeken him for their rueler and worldly lorde &amp; haue knowledged him for a kinge of the hoole worlde and ſo haue taken him / and hath alſo in al thinges bene wil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>linge obediente and obeiſſante vnto him / for thei haue delyured hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al their mony and goodes / and when they had now a longe ſeaſon co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued a wonderfull Rule of the which ther was neuer none ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che ſene / nor harde / and haue fortified and maede ſtronge the cite of Munſter in ſuche maner / that vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nother with gonne ſhot<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te nor aſſaute in no maner of means might no hurte be done vnto them / for many lordes &amp; other men of warre haeth proued it</p>
            <p>¶Vvhen now the people the which that laye before the cite did daeyly abyde and ſuffer greate ſkaethe and loſſe / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the lordes and ruelers conſidered that no ſchaethe nor hurte might be done vnto them of Munſter ſauinge oonly by famyſhinge / agreed the biſhop of Munſter with the lordes kapteins and men of armes and maede before the cite very ney ſeuen bolwarkes / the which ware well kept twelf monthe and moore with men of warre and ſoogers and did ſo greate ſkathe and horte vnto them of Munſter / that thei mighte get no prouiſion nor vittaels be no means in to the cite / nor noone from without the cite cowde nor might ſuccour nor helpe them the which is now wel manifeſte and knowen vnto all people.</p>
            <p>¶Vvhen now thei cowde nor myght haue of no body helpe nor comforte of vitayles or noriſhment for the body / and that dayely a greate ſubſtance of vitayles was ſpent and eaten by the multitude
<pb facs="tcp:13638:2"/>
of people / and the tyme ran faſt on from daye to daye / that the com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon people had eaten and ſpent their vitayles of meate and drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke / In ſo muche that thear was no moore ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes foode within the cite ſauinge oonly in the kinges place or pallaeis.</p>
            <p>¶Now had they in the cite in all voyde places open the walles &amp; aboute the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> where was any voide roume ſowed mooſt with peaſen and Raepes wherby the comen people louede a greate whyle vnto the tyme that they had eaten and ſpente the ſtrawe of the peaſon and the greane of the Raepes / and that all was eaten op that was in the cite ſaeuinge oonly thre horſſe / &amp; ther was none other mans foode in the cite / then horſſe and oxen heades / the which they toke and cotte them ſmall and did ſyethe them with water whyls they ware tender / and didde then eate them for to ſuſtayne their lyfe ther with all / For they ware dayly conforted thorowe their heade rueler caled kneppetelling that thear ſhulde come prouiſion in the cite / &amp; when that thear was none other comforte amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge the commen peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple but to dye for hongre / thei deſired to departe out of the cite / the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was the tromme ſtricken about the cite / that whoſoeuer deſired to departe out of the cite / and that wolde tary no lenger ther in / they ſhuld come to the kinge and he ſhulde geue them a token that they ſhulde be let owte.</p>
            <p>¶And ſtreight forth gathered thear togider a greate multitude of wemen yonge maydens and childerne / the which cam before the kinge and deſyerd to departe out of the cite / &amp; then cauſed the kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge theȝ to be ſearched &amp; to taeke awaye from them all that they had and lefte none of them moore than oone rayme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and ſayde to them now go your wayes to the heretiques. And when they ware out be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the gates without the cite betwene the caſt walles and the tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſches opo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a large place ther were thei fayne to abyde / for thei that laye vpon the bolwarkes let none paſſe thorow the trenſches / and ther moſt they eate leaues &amp; graſſe vnto the tyme that it was com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>manded them to departe out of the contre and thear was many of them founde dead the which had dyed for very honger. But all the ſougars or mens perſons that came out of the cite were al killed &amp; ſet vpon carte whyles aboute the cite / for the hegges and the trenſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches ware ſo hey &amp; ſo ſtronge that it was not poſſible to ſcape.</p>
            <p>¶Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> two &amp; fyfty ſowgers that lay in the cite of Munſter whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſaw that the honger was ſo greate &amp; was but ſmall prouiſion they agreed togither &amp; with a commen agreement to departe out of
<pb facs="tcp:13638:3"/>
the cete towarde the winge of ſainct Mauricius and deſyrede to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me vnto the biſchope him ſelfe / and when they had ſhowede theyr myndes vnto the ſowgars that ley vpon the bolwarckes and tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſches / and deſired to helpe them ouer the hedges and trenſches / then haethe the ſowgars of the Biſchop Reached them their haelbards and haue draewne them ſo ouer the hedges and tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſches lyke as they had promeſed them and that they ſholde helpe them to the biſchop / and when that they ware now holpen ouer the hed<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges and tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſches / the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dide the ſowgers of the biſchope ſee that the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they that ware com owt of the cete ware all cloothede with dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belettes of ſilcke and veluette and ſome of them had on clothe of golde lyke as they had taeken yt owt of the churches / when they ware now all within the trenſches then was thear noone oe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther counſell but drewe owt theyr ſwordes and killede the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all / the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was theare oone the whiche came Runnynghe behynde and was no yette ouer / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d whan he came ney vnto the hedge and trenſches and harde how they delte with his fellowes / not withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dinghe he Ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne to the hegde a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d boore halfe a haggeboſche the whiche fyred him ſelfe / and when he came ney to the hedge / oone offerede him his haelbarde to helpe him ouer as the oether his fellowes had bee<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne holpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ouer butte he proferede him his gonne a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſhotte him that he tomblede and ranne backe agaeyne into the cete / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d then was the kinge in his haele with his duekes the whiche he had maede butte a lytell before / with his gaerde and pete captaines a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d oether that had daeyle theyr lyuinge owt of his cowrte / and caſte amonge them that they hadde no longar vittaelles butt for tow monethes Deuyſinghe and cownſelinge the oone the oether / how that they might ghitte helpe and vittaelles. Then was theare oone amonge them all the whiche was calede hans of the longe ſtreate a watch maeſter and oone of the ruelers that the kinge ſette muche be and gaue him greate credite / the whiche had beene a longe ſeaſon befo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re with the biſchope oone of the maeſters of the trenſches / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d was goone from thence in the cete to the rebaptiſers / and this hans was very good teller of his taele a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d a greate taellaer in commenycatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and onder toeke a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d booſtede him ſelfe in the preſenſe of the kinge and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that had charge of the ruele of the cete / that as farre for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the as he coude or mighte haue charge of the kinge he knewe the meanes for to ghitte prouyſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of vittaeills within fowretene daeys a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to bringe in by that tyme thre hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derde me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of warre or ſowgers in to the cete where with the kinge a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d his cownſell ware wel co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tente a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d pleaſede / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d poynted a daey when this ſholde be to onderſtande opon midſommer nyghte / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d then was ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge ſtreate as at that tyme a watche maeſter i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the cete / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d had beene of the oether
<pb facs="tcp:13638:3"/>
ſyde withowte the cete a maeſter of the tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſches. In ſomuche that he knew boothe the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nar withoute the cete &amp; withi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the cete &amp; had veuede boothe by daey &amp; by nighte te circuyte a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the bolwarckes a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the diches abowte the towne wheare they ware deapeſte or ſhal loweſte wheare they ware broodeſte or narroweſte / and wheare the cete was ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſte / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d feebeleſte. In ſomuche that he knew all thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges / and as ſoene as he was lette owt of the cete knewe he ſtraight the righte waey thorrowe the hedge a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ouer the tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſches of his ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſaris the whiche he muſte paſſe / and ſo wente foure leegs from Mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſter in a lytell towne caled ham / and belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ghethe vnto te duke of cleeue And ſtreyght fourthe he ſente for oone the whiche was naemede my lorde of the dame and had his dwellinge theare / and had beene oone of the heades of Fryſla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / vnto the whiche he ſaei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de that he knew well that he was in greate indingnacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> withe the reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de biſchop of mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſter / for beacawſe that he had lefſte the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>knechts ſowgers vnto the Biſchope a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d was goone into the cete / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d he onder toeke as farre forthe as the biſchop wolde pardon him a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d geue him free gooinghe a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>minge he wolde geue his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence a mattar to knoelege wheare as londe and people laey on and as ſoene as my lorde of the dame had harde ſuche nyews he haethe nott taryede longe. Butte haethe geuen the biſchope knoele<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge thear of &amp; then haethe the biſchope geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him free goeynge and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>minghe / and haethe poyntede him a plaece wheare he ſholde co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me to him / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſo is the biſchope a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d his cownſell ſowne determine<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the broode ſtreate opo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the plaece apoynte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de togedder / &amp; haue deſyrede to heare the mattar / &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haethe ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken ſaeide vnto the biſchop and vnto his cownſell that he wolde ſhowe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the matter a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d as farre fowrthe as the mattar we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde then dorſte he neuer in his lyue daeys come amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge no lantſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>knechts nor ſowgers / and as farre forthe as the Biſchope wolde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> keape him all his lyfe daeis or geue him as muche as he might mantene him ſelfe opon dueringhe his lyfe / that then he wolde de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leuer vnto the biſchop opo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> midſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer night at ten of the clocke the cete of mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſter drey foetede / wheare opon the biſchope a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelers haethe taeken and holden a ſhorte cownſell / and be ſoune agreede in the mattar / and as farre forthe as the mattar came to affecte then wolde the heades with all oether ruelers by in the for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>warde / whear opon the biſchope haethe kepte a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons opon euery bolwarcke / and geuen alſo knoelege of the mattar vnto euery man / how they ware myndede for at ſuche an owre ſholde the cete be openede how they ware myndede theare to / and whether that they wolde auonture yt / for all noble men lordes gentell men
<pb facs="tcp:13638:4"/>
and thei that haue charge of oether ſhall &amp; will be of the furſt / and theare with was the comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te very well contente / &amp; cryed all with one voyce Ie / Ie / Ie / we haue layne long ynoughe in the ſtrawe we will alſo ſleape oones vpon beddes / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſo haeth the byſhope conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded accordinge to his promeſſe vnto hanſken of the longe ſtreate after his awne deſyre and Requeſte as had bene deuyſed. And ſo are concluded in oone and haue apointed togither that thei ſhulde be opon the ſette owre reddy a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d come before the croſſe gaete / &amp; then wolde he geue them a token a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d when thei ſhuld ſee the ſame / that they might then come hardely for all thinges ſhulde be cleare the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> After that went hanſken of the longe ſtreate into the cite agayne / and made the kinge beleaue that he had brought all thinges well to paſſe and that at the owre that he had apoynted ſhuld come in thre hondred ſowgers with prouyſion and vitailes. Then was the kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge and all that were aboute him very gladde and yoifull a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d maede the one the other good chyere / And now when the appointme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t was made fowrtene dayes a fore midſomer nighte / haue the folke of the biſhop prepared in the meane ſeaſon all thinges neceſſary there to lyke as ſkaellꝭ and ladders and other hookes / &amp; be come at the ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re apointed before the gate and then did hanſken of the longe ſtre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate geue them a token that al thinges were cleare / then haue they ſet forth / for hanſken of the longe ſtreate had bene the eaueninge be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore with the watche that watched that night vpon the rondel of the towre / &amp; ſayd vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for he was a watſchemaſter / this night ſhal many folkes and prouiſion come into the cite ſleape hardely / &amp; be of good chiere and be ſtil and take no hyde vnto the people that come in / and as now the folke of the biſhope thronge on ſoore then came to the ditches of the cite ney vnto a litel gate the which was ſhutte and locked a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d theare thei moſt neades ouer the diche / for the<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re was no place aboute the cite where the diche was narrower then theare as ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſken hadde tolde them before / and there they caſt their ladders ouer the diche a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d maede a brigge vnto the wal of the cite and when now many of them were ouer the diche went they forth tyl they came to the towre of the ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>del the which is caled the croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe gaete / &amp; thear caſte thei their ladders the which were a mans le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ghte to ſhorte ſo that thei coude do nothinge there / from thence ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte thei their Ladders opon the bolwarke of the rowndel and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were vpon the bolwarke thei drewe the oother op with their halbardes that thei ware thirte ſtronge. Then went thei vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the preuy watſche where as euery night watſched two / &amp; eyght vpon the towre of the rondell vnto the which hanſken of the lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge ſtreate had bene before / the firſte watcher that mette with them
<pb facs="tcp:13638:4"/>
they axed what the watſche worde was / then ſpake the watſche man &amp; ſayde earthe / &amp; ſtreight with all was thear oone with a two handed ſwerde and hewe him in two peces / for the watſche wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of them of Munſter within the cite was earth / and of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that were without the cite their watſche worde was Mary the mother of God / and they had for their feelde token / a ſtrawe wiſche vpon their armes. And then leaped forth the other watſchman and axed them what the watſche worde was and the folke of the biſhope an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſwered in lyke wyſe earth and theare with was he conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te / and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> went two or thre of them foerth lyke as watſchers and when thei were paſſed killed they the oether lykwyſe. After that went they ſtreight foerth to the other watſchers of the towre and axed them lykwyſe the watſche worde / and they ſayde alſo earth them thei kil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led lykwyſe / and then knewe thei the watſche worde well / and had taeken in the towre of the rowndell with al the gaetes &amp; bolwarc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes ſo that they cowde not wel be letted nor greaued. Then went they backwarde agayne to the bolwarcke / wheare as thei wolde ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue faſtened their ladders that ware a mans lenghte to ſhorte / but reached the other their halbardes and ſo drewe op the oether vpon the wael of the cite tyl they ware two honderd and fyfty ſtronge / &amp; then preaſed thei that ware out of the cite ſo ſore that the brigge the which they had maede ouer the diche brake. But when thei ſee that they ware two honderd and fifte ſtronge within the cite / then went they in the deade of the nighte and ſayde / now on gentil bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne folowe vs and mente that thei that ware yet out of the cite / ſhulde haue folowed them / and wente forth and founde the gates of the cite ſtandinge open / and ſo went foerth ſtil whils thei came to the markette place / and then began the daye to apere a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d al their trommes did ſtrike and thei cryed all alerm alerm / and ſpred abroo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de ſeuen banners / and then was the kinge and the citeſens firſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware that their ennemis ware afore and in the cite / and by and by had thei alſo gathered them togither / &amp; bette their ennemis with ſtronge honde from the market place backe againe vnto the gaete where as thei ware come in at / in the meane ſeaſon had one of the citeſens locked the gaetes that thei coulde not oute againe. Then cried the kinge gentill and deare lantſknechtes laye your weapens from yow and go againe out at the gates / yow ſhall haue no harme done vnto you / and ſtreight withall Ranne the women vppon the waelles and cryed to the ſowgars that they ſhulde fetche their banners and ther head agayne / for that kared nothinge the folke of the byſhope but ſtrooke vpon the gaetes with hamers and with axes / and as ſone as they hadde gotten the gaetes open / ranne they
<pb facs="tcp:13638:5"/>
ſtreight to the towre of the Rondell / and putte forthe their bannar owt at the towre towarde the bolwarckes from withoute the cete now ware the oether that might not come ouerthediche becauſe the brigge braeke Ranne backe agayne to theyr bolwarckes / for becau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe of the greate ſhuetinge and aſſaulte that they harde / in the cete and alſo they wente that all theyr fellowes had beene ſlaeyne / But whan they ſae the bannar opon the waell then concyderede they well that theyr compae<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gions waere yett alyue. Then Ranne they all to gedder in the cete and bette the kinge with all his rebapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers agayne from the markete plaece tyll vnto cathedrall courte / and thear they putte the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfe agayne in defence / and ware dryuen agayne from thence tyll vnto ſaeinct Michells chappell opon the whiche they didde greate hortte with ſhuetinghe / wheare thorrowe the biſchopes folke ſufferede greate ſkaethe and gaue backe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cawſe of the greate gonne ſhotte behynde the cathedrall churche / and ſo laey they opon ſaeinct Michells chappell whilles ten of the clocke afore noene / and in the meane ſeaſon was the kinge taeken the whiche was geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> backe opon ſaeinct Gillia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s gaete the whiche was the mooſte ſtrongheſte gaete of all the cete. After that they de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyrede to keape ſpeache with the oppermoſte captayne / the whiche was graented them.</p>
            <p>¶And was ſo moche done a boothe ſydes that euery oone ſhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de goo hoome vnto the comminge of their mooſte redoutede lorde and biſchope / then ſholde theare moore be ſpoken of the whiche was graentede and promeſede vnto them and opon that wente eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry oone in to his houſe / and when now the lantſknechts that had leyn vnder the biſchopes Bannar had ſuſtaynede greate loſſe and ſkaethe and the mooſte vallianſte and extymede gentill men and dubbell ſowgers that ware ſlayne to the nombre of a honderde and fyſte / Ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne they withe and angrey mynde in to the howſes and whe are they fownde any them drewe they be thy heare vpon the ſtrea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te / and hewed them to peces and ſo killed them. Schortely after was the trome ſtricken about that they ſholde kill no moo. Butte wheare any ware founde them ſholde they bringe to the oppermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte Ruelar / and when they ware brought thedder then was theyr heade ſtricken from theyr body / foure daeys after cauſede the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne to be ſtricken abowte with the trombe / that all weemen yonge &amp; olde ſholde comme to the do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me whiche is the cathedrall cherche and when they ware all thear and gaddered to gedder / was it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them that they ſholde by and by voyde the cete. And ſoo they voyded all yonge and olde to a greate nomber / opon the feal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de and that laſtede to the thirde daey. Butte whoo that cowde
<pb facs="tcp:13638:5"/>
agre withe the lorde for his wife or doughter or ſette ſeurte for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ware ſufferede to come in agayne / &amp; when they had bene aboute eyght daeis in the cete agaeyne they ſaeyde that they wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de abyde by their oolde ſecte / &amp; then was the trome ſtricke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboute agaeyne that all the weme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ware come in to the cete agayne ſholde come in the moerninge At nyne of the clocke to the plaece of the cathedrall churche.</p>
            <p>¶Then was geuen vnto them a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandmente of a nyew that they ſholde by and by voide the contre ionge and oelde a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d whoo ſo euer houſede or logede the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſholde be in treatede as tho he ware a Rebaptiſer him ſelfe he or ſhe a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d iff theare ware any ſowger that had any ſuche woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany / he moſte be ſonne ſette putte her awaey feo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him / or he hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfe ſholde ſuffer ſuche ponuyſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te of his bode as ſhe ſholde. Shortley after ware letters ſette vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all churche dores all gaetes of litell tounes and villaeges that ley a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute Mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſter that no bode ſholde nother houſe nor loge no ſuche folkes for they that ſholde be fownde ſo doeynghe they ſholde be ponniſſhed as a Rebaptiſer / ſo kan noman tell wheare that people is become. Item after that Iohu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ley a taellior and kinge of the Rebaptiſers of Mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſter / the whiche of al the rebaptiſers was choo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſen a kinge of nyewe Iheruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and of all the vnyuerſall worlde Is firſte after that the cete was all goten taeke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> preſonner / &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ware cauſede to be maede tow Ieron collours with longe linckes of Ieron opon them / oone for the kinge &amp; oone for his felloue knep pertellinge / the whiche ware ſtriken aboute their neckes / and faſte reuetede thre daeys after that they ware taeken preſonners / &amp; ware ſoo hadde betwene tow men of armes lyke beaſtes / thre leaghes of Munſter in a lytel toune caled Rybergh / and after that that the ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mey braeke op at Munſter / they ware brought vnto a caſtell caled dulem alſo thre leaghs from thence and thear paſſede many ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gars for by when they braeke op at Munſter / and than was the kinge and his fellowe kneppertellinge ſette a fore the gaete of the caſtell becauſe that the ſowgars ſholde yet oons moore ſe them in the paſſinge for be the caſtell.</p>
            <p>¶And the Biſchope of mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſter came vnto the caſtell firſte vnto the kinge and vnto his lyftennante kneppertrllinge / and as ſoene as the Biſchope ſaewe te kinge / ſpaeke hy to the kinge and ſaeide O yow wretſches hoe piteouſly haue yow diſtroyede my and my pouer ſubgeſts. Tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>werde the ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge ſpytfully &amp; ſkoornfully add ſaeide thou preeſte I haue notte diſtroyede the. I haue deleuerede the a ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge cete the whiche is agaeinſte all aſſaultes &amp; opru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>niges And I haue maede yow poure I will maeke yow riche agayne as
<pb facs="tcp:13638:6"/>
farre fourthe as yow will followe me cownlel. Then axede the Biſchope him hoche cede maeke him riche / then ſaeide he to the biſchope / I knowe well that yow will putte me to a ſhaemefull de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>athe. That he ſholde cauſe to be maede for him and for his lyfeten na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te kneppertellinge a kaege of Ieron keuerede ouer withe ledder and ſette the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> boothe thearin / and cauſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be carriede thorrone all contres / and who ſeuer deſyrede to ſee the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that they ſholde geue a ſtuyuer the whiche is tow pence flemiſche / they ſholde ghite moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne than the biſchope had laeide owte &amp; then the hoole biſcho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe Rick was worthe / and ſo is the biſchope depaerted from them</p>
            <p>¶Item whan te biſchope had now the cete agayne and all the rebaptiſers boothe men and wemen ware goone ſome ſlaeyne &amp; ſome voeydede the contre and dreuen awaey / and the lordes and the ſowgars ware agreede for the depaertinghe of the bowte ſoo that the ſowo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ars ſholde haue the oone halfe &amp; the lorde the oether. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was theare ſtricken aboute with the trome that noone of the ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gars ſholde keape as moche as the vallewe of half a golde ghil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and who that ware founde the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary ſholde be ponnyſchede of body and goods / and thear to ware .xxi. partinghe maeſters or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denede of euery bannar thre that ſholde ſell the goode a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d maeke yt to monne / then mente the men of armes a horſbacke to haue theyr paerte alſoo / the whiche the ſowgars wolde not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſente in no wyſe wheare of they ware longe at ſtryfe and debaete / &amp; when the paerte maeſters ſholde now departe the bowte and hadde not ſo moche monne as the ſowgars hadde countede / then toeke they the paerte maeſters euery oone and putte the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the middes of a ringe of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all as the maunar of them is / and demaended and axede of them wheare the monne and goodes ware become / and when the paerte maeſtres wolde not ſhowe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> according he vnto their mynde / cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed they the hangman to come in the middes of the ringe amonge them / the whiche drewe tow of the parte maeſters opo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a laddar a fore all the common ſowgars and yette wolde not they beknowen and this laſtede whills after noene / and then dide the lordes ſette owte the maetter tyll the next daey and in the mooringe ware all the parte maeſters goone / and then came the hagman in the ringe and ſaeide that it was forbidden him be the lordes that he ſholde axe no moore rigoroſly / co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cyderede that he hadde rackede the daey before and that they had not confeſſede. Then ſente they by a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d by of euery bannar tow ſowgars / and the hangman with them to the king and kauſede him alſo to be axede with tourmentes what he knewe of the bowte and when the hangman had tourmentede him threyſe knoelegede he of a barrel of golde and oether yewells and
<pb facs="tcp:13638:6"/>
and golden ringes / te whiche all was not ſo moche worthe as the ſowgars wolde fayne haue hadde.</p>
            <p>¶In concluſion then was the bowte depaertede amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge them ſo that euery ſowgar hadde no moore but eghtene eemde ghildeius of foure ſhillings flemmiſche the peece. Then faeide the heade me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſowgars they knewe a good remedy for as ſoene as they ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me owte of the gaetes they knewe wheare to haue mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne and a noe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lorde / and ſo wente the ſowgars awaey now ten now twente / and wente ſo awaey that theare aboode butte fyue honderde ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gars in the cete / the whiche the biſchope helde to keape the cete / &amp; who that oughte oone anoether they gaeue eche oether noothinge</p>
            <p>¶Item whoo that hadde letten him to be Rebaptiſede in Mun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſter and geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his goodes to the kinge that was perfection in their lawe / &amp; him dide the kinge hange a tooken abowte his necke maede of copper with thre letters thearin A.d.w.f the whiche betookene the ſo muche the woorde is become fleſche. Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before the kinge of mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſter was borne the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nar of a ronude boule with a golde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> croſſe theare opon / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d afore that tow ſwordes a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that betookenede as mu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che withe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as a ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge of the hoole vniuerſall worlde his cloothin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge and lifrey was broune and greane partede in foure quarters / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vpon the righte arme had he in mannar of an appell with a croſſe and tow ſwordes thutroe yt and theare withe hadde he cloethede all his gaerde and houſholde ſeruants. And when co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon people in the cete of Munſter had not had no breade in thre weckes / is theare neuertheleſſe fownde after that the cete was gotten in the kinges courte ſeuen to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of wyne and oone tonne of bier a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d oone tonne of fleſche &amp; a tonne of meele / and they ware wel in the cete of Munſter fyftene honderde men ſtronghe and when the cete was wonne they ware not paſte a thouſande and are of boothe ſydes be the warre that was before the cete and within ſlaeyne nye opon eght thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſande I beſeche Iheſu heauen kinge to ſende vs hence fourthe vnite and peas Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
